<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tears on the death of Evander occasioned by the lamentable losse of the truelie noble and generous, Sir. Iohn Svynton [sic] Knight, Collonel of an regiment of 2000 Nedderlanders, going for Venize, who was cast away by storme on the coast of England upon Goodwin sands the 13 of Octob. 1630. By G. Lauder.</title>
            <author>Lauder, George, b. ca. 1600.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05178</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15313</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109354</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845004</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845004</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9873</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05178)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9873)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1278:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tears on the death of Evander occasioned by the lamentable losse of the truelie noble and generous, Sir. Iohn Svynton [sic] Knight, Collonel of an regiment of 2000 Nedderlanders, going for Venize, who was cast away by storme on the coast of England upon Goodwin sands the 13 of Octob. 1630. By G. Lauder.</title>
                  <author>Lauder, George, b. ca. 1600.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Hagh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno D[omi]ni. 1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Swynton, John, --  Sir, d. 1630 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9873:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->
            <p>TEARS ON THE DEATH OF EVANDER <hi>Occaſioned by the Lamentable loſse of the truelie Noble and Generous,</hi> SIR. IOHN SVYNTON KNIGHT, Collonel of an Regiment of 2000 Nedderlanders, going for Venize, who was caſt away by ſtorme on the coaſt of England upon Goodwin ſands the 13 of Octob. 1630.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> G. LAVDER.</p>
            <p>HAGH Anno Dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i. 1630.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb facs="tcp:9873:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
            <lg>
               <l>THE Sunne in <hi>Thetys</hi> armes was gone to bed,</l>
               <l>And Nightes black curtaines ore this All were ſpred,</l>
               <l>Through which heavens glimpſeing lightes began t'appeare,</l>
               <l>And weakly ſparkle in our Hemyſpheere;</l>
               <l>When <hi>Lyſis,</hi> vhoſe free ſoule farre from the ſnaires</l>
               <l>Of Time; and worldly baſe entangling Cares,</l>
               <l>In quiet ſleep did prove the wished joye,</l>
               <l>Of ſueet repoſe which neuer dreames annoye,</l>
               <l>Whilst lull'd into a ſilence calme and deepe,</l>
               <l>Deaths Siſter did his ſenſes ſenleſse Keepe:</l>
               <l>Till rouzd with ſudden ſound amaz'd v'th feare,</l>
               <l>A voyce (he knewe full well) did peirce his eare,</l>
               <l>And calld him forth that darke and gloomie shade,</l>
               <l>To ſee a Ghost ſtand pale before his bed;</l>
               <l>A Ghost much like a Seagod, who did beare</l>
               <l>The Brave <hi>Evander's</hi> face his eyes and hayre,</l>
               <l>Yet as if drench'd into the fatal ſtood</l>
               <l>A woe full ſight there droppeing droopeing ſtood,</l>
               <l>And haveing wak'd both <hi>Lyſis</hi> eare and eye,</l>
               <l>Friſt stareing ſmil'd to ſee him panteing lie,</l>
               <l>At laſt theſe wordes did utter, which a groane</l>
               <l>Did ſadly usher, and hee thus went on.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lyſis,</hi> whoſe love and faith I liveing found,</l>
               <l>Where mortalls move, and <hi>Phoebus</hi> guilds te ground;</l>
               <l>Behold mee heere thy late <hi>Evanders</hi> ghoſt,</l>
               <l>A shaddowe of that ſubſtance thou haſt loſt.</l>
               <l>Who now whilſt Night with ſtarres doth ſeed the ſkies,</l>
               <l>Entreats thee open thy ſleep shutten eyes:</l>
               <l>It is no <hi>Demon</hi> on his browe that beares</l>
               <l>Miſchaunce and horror, and ſuch Maddeing feares,</l>
               <l>Bot a good ſoule whom death hath late ſett free,</l>
               <l>In love and freyndship that appeares to thee,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:9873:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
               <l>If ever mortall anguish greeffe and feare</l>
               <l>Seas'd any ſoule which could not find a teare,</l>
               <l>Bot ſenſeleſse made with too much ſenſe of woe,</l>
               <l>Poore <hi>Lyſis</hi> in that plight ſuch payne did knowe,</l>
               <l>For not one ſighe of breath came from his brest,</l>
               <l>And chilleing cold his members did inveſt,</l>
               <l>Tuo paſsions in his ſoule did keep a ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Feare of him dead and love of him on life,</l>
               <l>Bot love at last prevaill'd and call'd agayne</l>
               <l>His ſenſe and ſpeech in theſe ſad wordes to playn.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Deare Ghoſt (ſayd he) the object of my thought,</l>
               <l>And hath thy love from bleſt <hi>Elyſium</hi> brought.</l>
               <l>Thee backe agayne; enforceing heavens decree;</l>
               <l>Whith ah! too ſoone hath rob'd the world of Thee?</l>
               <l>O loyall freyndship! o hard povers of fate!</l>
               <l>O changing fortune! o wretch'd humane ſtate!</l>
               <l>O flattring hopes! o bodyes bot of glaſse!</l>
               <l>O lasteing greffes! o Ioyes which poasting paſſe!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Evander,</hi> once my hope thy cuntryes ioye,</l>
               <l>The world's regret, and now thy freynds annoye,</l>
               <l>And art thou gone ay Me! had Death the pover</l>
               <l>To bound thy Time; or haſte thy fatall hover?</l>
               <l>Ere thou hadst yett half honnors race outrunne</l>
               <l>Which was ſo brauelie but by Thee begunne?</l>
               <l>Thy ſommer ſeem'd in riſeing heatte to shine,</l>
               <l>Still lengthning, bot not yett com'd neare that line.</l>
               <l>At which thy loungeſt day should make a ſtand,</l>
               <l>Which now hath found her loungest Night at hand.</l>
               <l>The Laurells which thy ſuord should have lopp'd doune,</l>
               <l>To bind thy temples for thy merites croune,</l>
               <l>Though they there toppes both fayre and high did ſtretch</l>
               <l>And ſeem'd to be beyond the common reach</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9873:3"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->Of valors hand were yett too lowe for thee,</l>
               <l>Not fitt a garland for thy lockes to be.</l>
               <l>Bot now the Cypreſse hath uſurp'd that right</l>
               <l>Too Soone alace! thyne Obſequies to light.</l>
               <l>Thy youth which full of courage led thee on</l>
               <l>In ſearch of brave Occaſions, did it Wonne</l>
               <l>A reputation and a noble Name,</l>
               <l>In forrein warres, to prove o dyeing fame!</l>
               <l>That with thy life thy Name should buried lie</l>
               <l>And laſt bot like a lightning loungst the skie?</l>
               <l>No no, heavens Thee for greatter things ordain'd,</l>
               <l>And thou shouldſt have a higher ſpheare attayn'd'</l>
               <l>Thy bright <hi>Aurora</hi> augur'd greatter heatte</l>
               <l>And lounger day before thy Sunne should ſett,</l>
               <l>Which in his middayes glorie now gone doune</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Phaetons</hi> fall hath brought thy Night at Noone,</l>
               <l>If enuyous fates had not ecclypſt thy light</l>
               <l>Brave ſoule, hou had'ſt thou shin'd in <hi>Europe's</hi> ſight?</l>
               <l>The actions of thy firſt and tender yeares</l>
               <l>Aſtonish'd <hi>Holland</hi> yett for ſtrange admeires,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Iulliers</hi> ſawe thy forduard youth advances,</l>
               <l>Where leaders failld and feard the hurt of Chance,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bohemia's</hi> battles ſawe thee bath'd in blood,</l>
               <l>Out face all feare where death and horror ſtood,</l>
               <l>So deare <hi>Eliza's</hi> Croune was unto Thee</l>
               <l>That thou didst ſeeke a Sacrifice to be</l>
               <l>To her good fortune, and wouldſt glad appeaſe,</l>
               <l>Heavens frouneing browe if it thy blood could pleaſe,</l>
               <l>To ſettle on thy ſlaughtred bones a Throne</l>
               <l>For her and hers for aye to ſitt upon.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Ruſſian</hi> warres, and fierce <hi>Polonian</hi> fightes</l>
               <l>Sawe Thee a ſtranger work ſuch wondrous feattes,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9873:3"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->As made thy Name adoar'd, thy perſon lou'd,</l>
               <l>Thy ſword redoubted, and thy deeds approu'd,</l>
               <l>The wilde <hi>Hungariam</hi> did amazed veiue</l>
               <l>The terror-ſtricken misbeleeuing crue,</l>
               <l>Flie from thy ſight, wholle ſquadrons all at once,</l>
               <l>Whilst thou didst offer up the dyeing groanes</l>
               <l>Of ſuch as durſt thy kindled wrath abide:</l>
               <l>Vnto thy glorie, as they fainteing dy'd.</l>
               <l>Beſeeged <hi>Stade</hi> where <hi>Coeſars</hi> Eagles ſpred</l>
               <l>There conquering winges, and poverfull armies led</l>
               <l>All captive that the <hi>Romane</hi> pover withſtood,</l>
               <l>Within her ſtarved walles where want of food,</l>
               <l>And invard famine did more bandes orethrowe</l>
               <l>Then outvard force of an aſſaulting foe,</l>
               <l>Can give records of thy undaunted mynde</l>
               <l>Who ſcornd within her fortes to be confind;</l>
               <l>Bot bravelie ſallied out where dangers most</l>
               <l>And braveing Enemyes did ruine boast,</l>
               <l>Yea when all hope was loſt of more defence</l>
               <l>Knowes with what courage and what confidence,</l>
               <l>Thou fore'dst the Enemy a treattie yeeld</l>
               <l>And graunt thee paſſage free through open feeld.</l>
               <l>Theſe were bot preſages of greatter deeds,</l>
               <l>Though none more glorious in Times Annalls reads;</l>
               <l>For had thy late intentions come to end,</l>
               <l>What fortune did thy forduard armes attend?</l>
               <l>That Cittie, <hi>Neptunes</hi> love, had woundring ſcene</l>
               <l>Thy ſword enstale her all the Oceans Queene,</l>
               <l>To weare a Diademe as proud as <hi>Spayne</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Enrich'd with Iewells of the land and Mayne;</l>
               <l>Bot ah! fates would it nott, who what is brave</l>
               <l>As jealous of our good from us ſtill reave.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9873:4"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->Bot lett them doe there worſt ſince thou art gone</l>
               <l>In whom, true Honor and fayre vertue shone:</l>
               <l>Raiſe whom they liſt, and whom they liſt ſuppreſſe</l>
               <l>Change mirth in mourninge, Weell in wretchedneſse.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ah! had they yett ordained Thee to die</l>
               <l>In <hi>Mars</hi> his feeld; where in the worlds fayre eye</l>
               <l>Thou might have left a marke of thy great worth,</l>
               <l>For aftertymes to ſett thy glorie forth,</l>
               <l>Why was it not, O Greeffe! with ſuord in hand;</l>
               <l>In preſence of tuo Armyes in command?</l>
               <l>Where dy'd in blood and ſueatte, rage in thyne eyes,</l>
               <l>Sterne furie in thy lookes 'mongst fainteing Cries</l>
               <l>Of bleeding wightes, diſmembred unto Death</l>
               <l>Who with a deep fetchd ſighe, ſighe out there breathe</l>
               <l>That Thou didſt end, and in a lawefull warre</l>
               <l>Thy dayes with glorie which no Time could marre?</l>
               <l>Yett what doe I (Deare Ghoſt) thus wishe in vaine!</l>
               <l>Thou haſt enough, ſince heavens did ſo ordaine,</l>
               <l>With that his eyes now bigg with teares, ſett ope</l>
               <l>There Christall conduits and gave Greeffe free ſcope.</l>
               <l>The Ghoſt who ſawe his ſorrove in his eyes,</l>
               <l>With pittie mou'd did nott his love diſpiſe,</l>
               <l>Bot mildelie thus his paſsion did reſtrayne,</l>
               <l>And gentlie call'd him to himſelfe againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lyſis,</hi> my liveing freynd, and lover dead</l>
               <l>Forbeare thoſe playntes and teares in vaine to shed,</l>
               <l>Since heavens Who lent mee life a limite ſett</l>
               <l>Vnto my dayes: and I have reached that</l>
               <l>My death is too much honored, in the groanes</l>
               <l>Of thoſe my freynds, with whom I lived once,</l>
               <l>And that which now afflictes my greeved Ghoſt</l>
               <l>Is, that they waille too much what they have loſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9873:4"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->My Time was ſpent, and lifes short ſpanne was come</l>
               <l>To that last point where heavens would call mee home,</l>
               <l>My dayes a webb of wandring errors; wrought</l>
               <l>With wee land woe, mee through the world have brought,</l>
               <l>Bot ſtil with Hono'r which my loadſtarre was,</l>
               <l>In all my weyes and actions, ſtill my glaſse,</l>
               <l>For Honors love no danger I eshew'd,</l>
               <l>No force I fear'd, though greatter pover purſu'd,</l>
               <l>Bot still in chace of it, I bold did roame</l>
               <l>Throughout the corners of all Christiandome,</l>
               <l>What charge I bore when choſen to command,</l>
               <l>And with what care perform'd by this right hand,</l>
               <l>Lett thoſe for whom I fought be witnes all</l>
               <l>Whò Mee almoſt vnknowne to charge did call,</l>
               <l>Bott that's all paſt, and now my ſoule doth rest</l>
               <l>In peace, and finds the quiet of the Bleſt,</l>
               <l>I now from heavens highe roundes behold this Round,</l>
               <l>On which you live, lowe lowe, ſcarce to be found</l>
               <l>Bot of cleere eye; ſo ſmall a thing it is,</l>
               <l>Compair'd unto the Vniverſe of bleſſe;</l>
               <l>There you like Antes doe ſuarme, and ſtill at Iarres</l>
               <l>For leſse then title still wage deadly warres,</l>
               <l>And glorie to be great, on Earth ſo ſmall,</l>
               <l>As if there were no other world at all;</l>
               <l>Poore foolles! one day will let you ſee what oddes</l>
               <l>There is betuix Mans Empyrie and Gods,</l>
               <l>Bot thou my <hi>Lyſis;</hi> by thy love and faith</l>
               <l>Heark I conjure thee, what <hi>Evander</hi> ſayth,</l>
               <l>And let the world heare it againe from Thee,</l>
               <l>When Time shall give thee opportunitie,</l>
               <l>Though heavens in ſuelling waves my grave aſsignd,</l>
               <l>And made my obſequies the bluſtring wind:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9873:5"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->The <hi>Tritons</hi> and the <hi>Nereyds</hi> of the mayne,</l>
               <l>To grace my funerall pompe with goodlie trayne,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Neptunes</hi> ſelfe cheeffe mourner to deplore</l>
               <l>My Death; and bring the showe to <hi>Brittaines</hi> shoare,</l>
               <l>I enuy nott there hap whom <hi>Paros</hi> ſtone</l>
               <l>Dot shroude in ſtatelie Tombes by Time orethrone,</l>
               <l>The Chriſtall teares of thoſe my worthy freynds,</l>
               <l>Who now regrett my loſse, a tribute lends.</l>
               <l>To reare a Monument of love for Mee,</l>
               <l>Which will perhaps weare with Aeternitie</l>
               <l>In ſome one pairt, which <hi>Lyſis</hi> if it be</l>
               <l>My Ghoſt shall think she owes the ſame to Thee.</l>
               <l>So fare thou weell live honors lover ſtill,</l>
               <l>Heavens sheild thee with there love and mens goodwill,</l>
               <l>This ſayd Hee vanish'd, <hi>Lyſis</hi> weeping lay</l>
               <l>Vntill the Sunne had brought about the day.</l>
            </lg>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>Dignum Laude virum Muſa vetat mori,</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. LAVDER.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:9873:5"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
